Rong Jin

Curriculum Vitae

17490 Meandering Way APT 1710
Dallas, TX75252

© Contact: 469-407-8434

⋈ rong.jin@utdallas.edu

Research Interests

My research interests are in Data Science and Machine Learning, including data-driven computation and optimization in online social networks analysis. In addition, I am interested in interactive Multimedia Systems for STEM education, with emphasises in 3D tele-immersion virtual reality system, scaffolded learning system, and evaluation study for maximizing quality of user experience.

Education

2015 - Now Ph.D. Candidate Computer Science, University of Texas at Dallas

Advisor: Dr. Weili Wu

Research areas: Data Science, Social Networks, Multimedia Systems, STEM education

2013 - 2015 M.S. Computer Science, University of Texas at Dallas

2007-2011 B.Eng. Communications Engineering, Nanjing University of Posts & Telecommu-

nications

Thesis title: Interface Design for FFT sequential and parallel computing

Advisor: Prof. Ming Zhang

Honors and Awards

2019 ACM SIGSIM-PADS Student Travel Grant

2017 2017 Grace Hopper Conference (GHC'17) Scholarship

2017 CRA-W Graduate Cohort Scholarship

2012-2015 Cisco CCNA Certificate in Routing & Switching (CSCO12429154)

2007 - 2011 Academic Performance Fellowship (2nd, 3rd Prizes)

Publications

1 book chapter, 2 refereed journal papers, 5 full refereed papers (4 conference, 1 workshop)

Book Chapter Rong Jin, Weili Wu, My T. Thai, and Ding-Zhu Du. 2020. Black Box and Data-Driving Computation. In Book Black Box Optimization, Machine Learning and No-Free Lunch Theorems, Springer, Cham. (To appear)

JOCO Qiufen Ni, Smita Ghosh, Chuanhe Huang, Weili Wu, and **Rong Jin**. Discount allocation for cost minimization in online social networks. submitted to the *Journal of Combinatorial Optimization (JOCO)*. (under review).

TKDD Baokun He, Guihong Wan, **Rong Jin**, and Haim Schweitzer. The Bias Method for Robust Centered Principal Component Analysis. submitted to the *ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from Data (TKDD)*, April 2020. (under review).

COCOA'20 Shengminjie Chen, Wenguo Yang, Suixiang Gao, and **Rong Jin**. Novel algorithms for maximum DS decomposition. submitted to *The 14th Annual International Conference on Combinatorial Optimization and Applications (COCOA'20)*, Dallas, Texas, USA, December 11-13, 2020. (under review).

- SIGSIM- Midori Kitagawa, Paul Fishwick, Michael Kesden, Mary Urquhart, Rosanna Guadagno, PADS'19 Rong Jin, Ngoc Tran, Erik Omogbehin, Aditya Prakash, Priyanka Awaraddi, Baily Hale, Ken Suura, Aniket Raj, James Stanfield, and Henry Vo. Scaffolded Training Environment for Physics Programming (STEPP): Modeling High School Physics using Concept Maps and State Machines. In proceedings of the 2019 ACM SIGSIM Conference on Principles of Advanced Discrete Simulation (SIGSIM-PADS'19), Pages 127–136, Chicago, Illinois, USA, June 3-5, 2019. (Oral)
- IWISC'18 Lakshmi Sharma, Rong Jin, Balakrishnan Prabhakaran, and Murry Gans. LearnDNA: An Interactive VR Application for Learning DNA Structure. In proceedings of the 3rd International Workshop on Interactive and Spatial Computing (IWISC'18), Pages 80-87, Richardson, Texas, USA, April 12 -13, 2018. (Oral)
 - ISM'17 Kevin Desai, Suraj Raghuraman, **Rong Jin**, and Balakrishnan Prabhakaran. QoE Studies on Interactive 3D Tele-Immersion. 2017 IEEE international symposium on multimedia (ISM 2017), Pages 130-137, Taichung, Taiwan, Dec. 11 -13 2017. (Oral)
- BigMM'17 Kevin Desai, Uriel Haile Hernndez Belmonte, **Rong Jin**, Balakrishnan Prabhakaran, Paul Diehl, Victor Ayala Ramirez, Vinu Johnson, and Murry Gans. Experiences with Multi-Modal Collaborative Virtual Laboratory (MMCVL). 2017 IEEE Third International Conference on Multimedia Big Data (BigMM 2017), Pages 376-383, Laguna Hills, California, USA, April 2017. (Oral)

Research Experiences

3/2020 – Now **Research Assistant**, Data Communication and Data Management Lab. (publication work is ongoing.)

Working on rumor source detection in online social networks using mathematical methods in data science, optimization, approximation algorithms and machine learning.

9/2019 - Research Assistant, Computer Vision and Data Lab.

3/2020 (For references see paper TKDD)

Worked on feature extraction with big data using numerical methods and statistical tools including PCA, CSS and randomized algorithms analysis for big sparse data.

01/2018 - Research Assistant, Creative Automata Lab.

08/2019 STEPP project: Learning Physics in a Synergistic Scaffolded Programming Environment (NSF No.1741756)

(For references see paper SIGSIM-PADS'19 and https://stepp.utdallas.edu/)

Part of my research work was modeling, developing and implementing STEPP environment system:

- \bullet Worked on the the development of the in-house built physics system using Unity game engine.
- Worked closely with the UX team to improve the functionality and experience of the application and deliver results within the stipulated deadline.
- I am also one of contributors to project VIGOR.
- 12/2016 Research Assistant, Multimedia Systems Lab.
 - 12/2017 (For references see papers BigMM'17, ISM'17, IWISC'18, and Demos URLs below)

Part of my research was proposing and developing a Multimodal Collaborative Virtual Laboratory (MMCVL) system that is extended from Multi-modal 3D tele-immersion project. I conducted projects about STEM-domain scaffolded 3D immersive virtual learning environment which assists community college students to learn theoretical or experimental concepts (i.e. How to read a meniscus; How to use hydrometer; Leaning RNA transcription and translation processes) in virtual collaborative chemistry/biology lab. All of projects are built on Unity game engine and TIGER (Tele-Immersive Gaming Environment and Resources) system from Multimedia Systems Lab, which facilitates virtual collaboration among a distributed set of humans by using 3D cameras such as Microsoft Kinect. Projects may also apply with Oculus rift, MYO armband, and Leap Motion gesture tracking. The data management server is using SQLite and WAMP. The interface between users and VR system is using HTML webpage for logging in.

1. How to read a meniscus

• Two experiments demos: Experiment 1, Experiment 2

2. How to use Hydrometer

- Kinect + Myo Armband Version: Demo
- Oculus Rift + Leap Motion Version: Demo
- 3. Learning RNA transcription and translation processes

 Demo

Research Assistant, Institute for Data Analytics.

12/2016 E-PLAN: Emergency Response Information System for first responders in US.

Part of my research work was upgrading E-PLAN Real-Time Chemical Plume Mapping & Geographic Information Reporting System with new versions Google Maps API and weather retriever API.

Presentations

08/2016 -

Poster STEPP presented at Integrating Computational Thinking Conference, College Park, MD, May 2019

Poster Leveraging UTeach Dallas Outreach to Test Interactive Unity-Based Simulations for Physics Education 2018

Demo International Workshop on Interactive and Spatial Computing (IWISC) 2018

Demo DCCCD STEM Summit 2017

Teaching Experiences

Teaching Assistant

Summer2020 CS 6364 Artificial Intelligence

Spring 2020 CS 4391 Introduction to Computer Vision

CS 6384 Computer Vision

Fall 2019 CS 4384 Automata Theory

Fall 2017 $\,$ CS 4332 Introduction to Programming Video Games

Spring 2017 CS 3376 C/C++ Programming in a UNIX Environment

CS/STAT 6301 - R for Data Scientists

Summer2016 CS/STAT 6301 Advanced Computational Methods for Data Science

Spring 2016 CS/STAT 6301 Advanced Computational Methods for Data Science

Fall 2015 CS 6363 Design and analysis of Computer Algorithms

Grader

Summer 2015 CS 4375 Introduction to Machine Learning

CS 6375 Machine Learning

Spring 2015 CS 4391 Introduction to Computer Vision

CS 6384 Computer Vision

Mentoring

Mentored the projects of four graduate students and one undergraduate student.

- Bryant Nguyen (BS, UT Dallas)
- Lakshmi Sharma (MCS, UT Dallas, co-authored [IWISC'18])
- Scott Fontenarosa (MCS, UT Dallas)
- David Butler (MCS, UT Dallas)
- Hiranya Garbha Kumar (MCS, UT Dallas)

Professional Service

Reviewer Theoretical Computer Science(TCS) 03/2020 - Present

Discrete Mathematics, Algorithms and Application (DMAA) 03/2020 – Present

IEEE Transactions on Multimedia (TMM) 03/2016 - Present

Simulation: Transaction of the Society for Modeling and Simulation International 2019

Sub-Reviewer ITCAI 2019

Memberships Graduate Student Member for IEEE 01/2017 – Present

Graduate Student Member for ACM, ACM W & SIGMM 02/2017 - Present

Graduate Student Member for ACM SIGSIM, 03/2019 - Present

Technical Skills

Proficient Python, Numpy, SciPy, Sklearn, Pandas, SQL, DBMS, LATEX

Familiar Tensorflow, C#, C++, HTML, CSS, JavaScript

Applications Git, AWS, Game Engine

OS Linux, Windows, MacOS

Industry Experience

2011 – 2012 Software Engineer in Test, Infosys, Shanghai, China.

Professional References

Available upon request.